I'm going to announce that from my chest if you'll tell us about the K-theory of the
complex numbers.
Oh, thank you.
It's very nice to be here giving a talk.
So this is about the K-theory of the complex numbers, and it's a joint work with.
I mean, it's kind of very, there's no big theorems or anything.
It's kind of a long term project of mine.
Basically, the goal was to ask the right question and then maybe the answer.
Well, I don't know when the answer might come, but maybe someone.
Yeah, we'll see.
So I hope at least I'll ask the right question by the end of the talk.
So let me by way of background, let me start with a reminder about algebraic K-theory
before specializing to the case of the complex numbers to talk about the general situation.
So let's say we have maybe not too general.
I'm going to take a ring, but I'm going to assume it's commutative.
And there's two reasons for that.
One is that later on in the talk, some kind of tensor product will be important.
And the second reason is that I don't have to say left or right.
So then I recall that K zero bar.
You take a free abelian group on the set of finitely generated projective R modules.
And you want out by some relations, which says that you said this equal to this.
There's this nice morphism from M to and direct some key.
This is kind of the familiar thing.
So kind of a universal place where dimension like invariants reside.
But I'm not just interested in K zero.
There's a reason why the zeros there, the classical algebraic K-theory.
But I'm also interested in the higher algebraic K-theory.
And the story there is that, in fact, there is a homotopy type.
And I won't give you a precise definition of this homotopy type, instead, I'll tell you the classical thing.
And I'll just give you a specific definition of this homotopy type.
But I'm also interested in the higher algebraic K-theory.
And the story varies.
In fact, there is a homotopy type.
this classical thing. And I won't give you a precise definition of this homotopy type,
instead I'll tell you things. For example, one thing I can tell you is that
you can think of kind of, so this homotopy type, it doesn't, so you have a set of components,
the pi zero, which is the usual k zero, but then you also have this pi one,
let's say you gained an understanding of k zero, so you maybe have some list of
representatives for all, or list of elements in this k zero group, and then you give yourself
a finitely generated project of our module, then you have some understanding of how to equate it
with something in this list. But maybe there's different ways you can, using these relations,
move your module around to get it to equal to one of the representatives in that list.
And you can kind of, if you squint enough, you'll see yourself tracing some sort of path in some
space, and then maybe you can also trace loops in that space, and that's kind of what pi one would
be. And you can try to identify k one in that manner, and then if you identified k one, there
may be some ambiguities in how you identified representatives for all the loops, and that would
give you something like k two and so on. And you can make this into a formal definition, and even
more miraculously, with lots of hard work, sometimes you can even calculate these k groups
in various simple cases. Okay, and that's one thing I wanted to say about these higher k groups.
Another thing I want to say is, to give an example of fields, so
so if r equals k is a field, simplest thing, then there's something we all know that finite
dimensional vector spaces are classified by their dimension. Since we group completed,
that gives us integers. k one of k is k cross, so that's the ambiguity in fixing our one-dimensional
vector space, but it turns out that up to some simple rules, the ambiguity in fixing an arbitrary
dimensional vector space reduces to that in the one-dimensional vector space, meaning you get k
cross. And then the fun thing is, you can actually give a presentation for k two, this is called
Matsumoto's presentation. Now it gets a bit more involved, so here implicitly I'm using some
multiplicative structure, but okay, so
so yeah, so there's you take the, okay, this is an abelian group under multiplication,
so I think of it additively actually, in this incarnation it's actually best thought of as an
additive group, and you take that tensor product with itself as abelian groups, and then you mod
out by a single family of relations called the Steinberg relations, they're parameterized by
elements of the field different from zero and one, and you get some big groups this way,
and that turns out to be what k two is, and it's a little bit more tricky to give
explicit descriptions once you go farther down the line, I mean for general k. Okay,
that's another thing I wanted to tell you, the next thing I want to tell you or ask with that,
we'll ask the question together, is why do we care? Why do we care about higher algebraic k
theory? Well probably there are many different reasons, but there's one that's maybe closest to
my heart that I certainly want to mention, which is that k theory is strongly related to something
called motivic cohomology, and motivic cohomology is strongly related to something perhaps
conjectural, which is x groups, or maybe it's equal to, I don't know, in some category of mixed motives,
and these are realization functions,
and you get things like x in Galois representations,
or if you're over the complex numbers, x in mixed odd structures,
whatever other realizations you have, and so what you can think of k theory class as kind of a,
well it's motivic in the sense that it gives this universal source for
kind of data you might see here, an extension of Galois representations,
essentially mixed odd structures, kind of one object that gives rise to all
those different things in different worlds. That's one aspect, but the other aspect,
but that would be not worth much if it, I mean, if there weren't some reason why this
could be understood, and there is a very good reason why this can be understood, and it's that
k theory is basically just linear algebra, I mean, it's all just about vector space,
finite dimensional vector space. You take the category of finite dimensional vector
spaces, you do something with it, but in the end it's just linear algebra, right, so
that actually does make it easier to study in many ways.
There, for example, to understand this, you need to know, not just linear algebra,
you need to know about things like polynomials, those are complicated,
I mean, yeah, but somehow there's a relation. Okay, I wrote some things here, I wrote Beilinson in here,
and oh yes, and I wanted to say this actually kind of works, I mean, I think the only reason
we know things about X and mixed-tape motives over the rational numbers, for example, is because
we can understand enough about general linear groups, the NGLNZ and its cohomology due to
Quillen and Borel and Borel-Serre, so really, I mean, this path of going from linear algebra to
this kind of fancy stuff actually works, at least in some cases. Okay, so well, okay, so then coming
back to KFC, well, when I said that it sounded like KFC,
all right, I'll be here all week, so this, whatever this is, it should have to do with,
following this Beilinson line here, it should have to do with cohomology theories,
over the complex numbers, that's kind of, that's what we're interested in,
in probing here, when we talk about the K theory of complex numbers. Okay, any questions?
cohomology theories of what?
Details come later. In principle algebraic varieties.
But therein lies the problem, let's be segway into the next. So what is the problem? By the way,
I have a record, and the first time I gave a talk about this topic was eight years ago,
almost to the day, and so I've actually been thinking about this for a long time. So what's
the problem? So well, K theory, this construction K theory only refers to the abstract field
C. So it's going to be the same for C as for any, so algebraically closed, characteristic zero,
cardinality, continue. It's going to be the same for any field with those properties,
it doesn't know that T is a very special field that has a topology,
a tendon geometry and so on. So let's look at this more concretely. So
I invite you to try to ponder the structure of this K2 group, or lack thereof,
and somehow take into account the topology of the complex numbers or something else. It's really
quite messy. I mean, so in fact, there's a theorem of Milner, which is, I'll say it loosely,
you can try to put a topology on this, but in any case, the maximal house door quotient
is zero. So this is a huge group, make no mistake, but it's all chaotic.
So this suggests
whatever it may mean, the completed K2
should be zero.
With K0 and K1, there's no problem. Z and C cross are perfectly
reasonable things, but once you get to K2, things get a bit funny. But on the other hand,
it can't be true that the completed, whatever it means, that the completed things should be zero
in all degrees bigger than one, because they're a regulator maps.
K2 and minus one of the complex numbers goes to C mod 2 pi i,
regulator, regulator maps, this being for n bigger than zero.
So there are, and we know these maps are non-trivial, because we map K of K2 and minus
one of Z in there, you get something interesting. So in odd degrees, in positive odd degrees,
there should be something reasonable inside these, or some reasonable, maybe quotient,
you can think of it, it's probably not a quotient, something reasonable that is maps to, okay,
something reasonable that is maps to, okay, even though in the individual groups themselves
will have the same problems as in the K2 case, there'll be some wild stuff,
a non-house store for crazy looking things. So now I will ask the vague form of the,
or present it, let me say the vague form of the question, or a variety of questions.
So, does there exist a stated variance?
The algebraic k-period of the complex numbers, capturing regulators,
how to calculate it,
and what is the relation to cohomology theories?
And say, is there more than just regulators?
Just regulators, yeah, right.
So those are the kind of questions I want to address, or no, I want to make precise, yeah.
But are there any, do you have any questions for me right now?
Okay.
What is the relationship to KU?
To KU? Well, KU, I mean, you know, KU is like just this part, bumped up to the next degree.
Well, it's like, if you take the homotopy, if you imagine taking the homotopy type of this,
turns into a circle, that's like a Z in the next degree, and that's, you've seen KU even,
Does that mean the answer to is there more than just regulators will be no?
Well, I think there's an underlying false assumption behind your question,
which is that this completed variant will be KU.
I mean, it's definitely more refined than KU. It should map to KU, but it should be more refined.
So I think, because it should see these things, and not just these things in the next degree.
Could I answer your question?
Yes, maybe. Okay. Maybe your question will make more sense later.
Okay. So next topic is
candidate, candidate complete.
So let me give the basic idea.
So well, what was K of C based on linear algebra, finite dimensional complex vector spaces.
But this is bad because it only uses C as an abstract field.
And then the complete thing, which I'll switch to calling an analytic thing.
So this will be based on a certain topological, let's see vector spaces.
Let's see if I can.
Well, wait, because I'm going to pull the rug out from under your feet immediately.
So, well, okay. But there's a problem with this. Interpreting this too naively leads to problems.
Namely that categories of interesting, non-finite dimensional categories of topological vector
spaces tend to have island-bridge spindle.
So there's maybe some completed infinite direct sum of any object and to direct sum your original
thing with that, it doesn't change it. And this gives a relation X equals one plus X and K theory,
which proves that one equals zero. And the whole thing has to match. Hilbert Hotel, yeah.
So let's see if I can answer your question.
So if you interpret this too naively, your completed K-theory is just going to be zero,
ever completely, just totally zero.
So we need a new idea.
And thankfully, a new brilliant idea, which I'm going to talk about in a moment,
is that we're going to have a new idea, and we're going to have to change it.
And thankfully, a new brilliant idea was provided by Aleksandr Efimov. So this is
then to the new theory of K-theory, or extended the context of algebraic K-theory.
And let me explain how it goes. Without giving details, although I'll give more and more details
as I discuss the example I care about. But first, I won't tell you anything, but then, yeah, okay.
I'll just set the stage. So what did we have? We had finite dimensional, I'm going to stick to C,
yeah, we have finite dimensional, or no, well, finally generated projective R-modules.
The first thing you have to do is change the context a little bit. You have to go
derived. This is not the most important part of it, but it's something you do have to do
to get the theory to work. So you replace this by perfect complexes of R-modules.
And again, there's a version of K-theory. So where K0 is a free abelian group generated by
all perfect complexes. And now the relation you write down is that the class of M equals the class
of M plus the class of P, if there exists a co-fiber sequence. So MPM, so distinguished
triangle broad category in the homotopy category. And it's the same as the K0 you had here. That's
not difficult to see just by resolving your perfect complexes. So here you're thinking of
universal Euler characteristics. Here you're thinking of universal dimensions. It's the same
thing. And that also extends to the hierarchy. You can also define hierarchy groups here. And
it also is the same as the hierarchy groups you have here. That's not as easy to see, but okay.
So you want to work in this kind of derived context as a first, but then the real change comes next.
So what, first of all, what kind of an object is this? This is well, it's some kind of
derived, small, small derived category. So let's say a small,
and let's also say idempotent complete, stable infinity category.
And now here's the cool thing. So the Lurie showed that this world actually has an enlargement.
The category of these kinds of categories sits naturally inside of a larger category of other
categories. So small, stable, idempotent complete, infinity categories. The category of those sits
fully faithfully inside of something called dualizable, presentable, infinity categories.
So these are big categories. They don't have a set's worth of objects anymore. They're generated
under co-limits by a set's worth of objects, but they are big. And the morphisms here in this category
are those co-limit preserving. I apologize for my handwriting. Just listen to my words.
And my writing is just there to slow me down, co-limit-preserving-functorist-movement-pro-limit-preserving
right-adjoint. So that's a mouthful, right? Okay. And then what is this inclusion implemented by?
You have a small category, and you take its in category.
And then you have a small category, and you take its in category.
And you can see that this condition on morphisms on the level of in categories is just the condition
that means that it corresponds to a functional level of small categories. So it commutes with
co-limits, so it's determined by what it does on C. Then the condition on the right-adjoint means
that C has to go to D, such a function in C to in D. And the important condition is the dualizable,
and this means close enough to compactly generated.
And I'm not going to make that precise again until later in the talk.
Suffice it to say that they're in some sense controlled by compactly generated categories,
but they do not themselves have to be compactly generated. So this is what I mean by pulling a
rug out from under your feet, because we like being compactly generated. It's great. But now
I really believe we have to learn to get there. It turns out there are so many interesting examples
to be categorized. People never even noticed before looking into this. They do all sorts of
things for you. We have to get used to not having enough compact objects. There's another reason
for that. I just realized staring at Tomer in the audience. Okay. Right. Okay.
So I'm claiming, I claim these things are everywhere, but I'm not going to give an example yet.
Is it normal that these boards are so difficult to move?
They're actually weak.
I have one advantage though.
Okay. Right. So I have to, I'm afraid this is all very abstract and I didn't even give you
examples, but I have to introduce you also to a variant, which actually helps to produce examples.
So there's an analog of this whole story
with tensor structure included.
So there I would say the thing to put on the, on the small side is small, stable infinity categories
with symmetric monoidal tensor product and all objects are dualizable.
So again, perf R, if R is a commutative ring, is a perfectly nice example.
This embeds into what are called rigid presentable symmetric monoidal
infinity categories, stable infinity categories.
These were investigated, but defined and studied by Gates, Gorey, Rosenblum.
And so it's some big tensor categories. Okay. And again, the function that implements this is C
goes to even C. And there's something nice over here, which is that here I want, you know,
and morphisms here are co-limit preserving tensor functions.
And a nice thing here is that the right, it all automatically has a right to join the commutes
and co-limits. So that weirdness that you had to have that extra property disappears here.
You can kind of, you can verify that and there's things in the essential image here because
it's a tensor functor. So it has to send dualizable objects to dualizable objects,
but the hypothesis is guaranteed that dualizable is the same thing as compact. So yeah.
Can you say, reading here, your notion is generated under dualizable?
No, no, I haven't said what it means. And if not that,
it's a,
so then the main theorem, so this is a fema,
k-theory naturally extends
to dualizable categories.
Meaning the k-theory functor from this thing to spectra, whatever you like, or kn for any n,
functor to a abelian groups, canonically extends to a functor from this category to the same
target. The k-theory here factors through this included, meaning there's a bigger world in which
algebraic k-theory can be defined. For things of the form in C, it's just you pass the compact
objects and take the normal k-theory you know there. For things not in the form in C, it's not
that. Nothing new and mysterious. Okay? And also, yeah, if C is rigid, then K of C gets a ring
structure. Morally speaking, the tensor product on C induces a ring structure on K of C, just like
usual. Okay, now here's a nice fact that inclusion from rigid presentable stable tensor categories
into all presentable stable tensor categories has a right of choice.
Oh, the rigidification. So now you see that these things really are everywhere. You take any
tensor category you happen to run across, you hit it with this, you get something rigid, and surprisingly
enough, it's very rarely compactly generated. You produce something genuinely new, even if you start
with a very familiar one of these. Even if you start with one that's actually compactly generated,
but not rigid. You apply rigidification, you get a new category is rigid and not compactly generated.
So really, these things are everywhere, and they're extremely, yeah, well, yeah.
And so if the unit in C is compact, then even better, this C ridge is actually sitting
faithfully inside C. And how to think about this, it's a C ridge is an improved version
of taking into the set of dualizable objects.
In this case, where the unit is compact. It's bigger than that, and it's not compactly generated.
Okay, again, I will say more about this and how it actually works when we when I get to the example
I care about, but I don't want to say too much about examples that aren't in the focus of the
talk because I want to get through some things. Okay, so now what are we going to do? I'm still
in this section candidate complete K of C. Is this block accurate? Could I ask?
I don't know if my phone is out of batteries. It's a couple of minutes fast. It's 501. Thank you.
It's an hour plus. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I'm in modulo 60. Yeah.
Okay, so what we're going to do is we're going to produce instead of thinking about trying to
produce a small category and taking cases that we're going to produce a large category,
take the cater in this new sense. We don't even have to worry about producing a dualizable one
as long as you produce a tensor category, we can just rigidify it at the end. Now here's a
here's it. So here's a experimental fact.
If C is any reasonable, I don't know, reasonable. I mean, this is not a mathematical fact, right?
This is if this is any presentable stable infinity category with tensor product
whose objects
feel like some kind of complete topological C vector spaces. Okay, there's millions of options
for what you could mean by a topological C vector complete topological C vector space
based on Banach spaces, whatever, Hilbert spaces, whatever you want. But a fact, an empirical fact
is that whatever choice you make, once you rigidify, you always get the same thing.
You always get the same thing. So you get something truly canonical.
So all of the subtlety of infinite dimensional topological vector spaces,
different kinds of convexity properties, whether you have
Banach, you know, open balls fundamental or compact set, the kind of dual thing where compact
compact sets are fundamental. Once you can make categories that encode any of them,
but once you rigidify, you always get the exact same thing. This is the main thing
I want to advertise is there really is a canonical choice for
linear algebra and infinite dimensions topological vector spaces.
So think of this as some version of the phenomenon that the
finite dimensional vector space has a unique topology.
Sure, that sounds good. Yeah, maybe I will from now on.
So I'm the experimentalist, maybe you're theoretical.
Right. So I won't, I will tell you my, or our, I should say preferred way of.
So this will be that you have everything that's derived. This is including experimental
observations about how you resolve one kind of weave. Like this is include facts like how
you would resolve like Banach space by compact type things, how you resolve a compact type
thing by balance. It has all these resolution factors. Yeah.
It does nothing to do with seeing it, but also, well,
I might get to non-archimedean stuff at the end of the talk.
It turns out in the non-archimedean world, there's actually maybe two choices,
but you're happy. There's a choice in the non-archimedean world that doesn't exist
in the Archimedean world and it's the easier one. Okay. Other questions.
Okay. Oh, sure. Yeah. I'm about to explain that it's extremely general.
Yeah. So, so what's, so I'll give you one, our, our preferred C 10 big C tensor,
which we can rigidify. So, yeah, maybe I also take the opportunity to advertise that
Peter and I are currently teaching a class on, on analytic stacks, where we propose new
foundations for analytic geometry. And they're being posted on IHS's YouTube site and so on.
And now I'll make contact with that course to some extent. So if let's, well, there's,
there's many different things you can start with as your familiar input data,
but let me just take an arbitrary bond offering with the norm specified.
And from such a thing, you can produce an analytic stack in our sense. So
liquid, so-called liquid analytic stack associated to this. And every such thing has a derived
category. And it's one of these C tensor guys. But it's not rigid, but you can then rigid rigidify
it. And then you get something that I claim that all the steps are canonical, but certainly
this composition of steps is, is canonical. You might bicker a bit about how we set the
foundations up, but it doesn't mean the composition is certainly canonical.
And so if, if this is a trivial norm, so basically if you're thinking of this as being discrete,
then what is this? It's D, R, truth, liquid, bridge. It's just the usual
big derived category of R. It's compactly generated and this K theory is the usual K theory of R.
But now when we fit it into a machine where we don't need to plug in a discrete ring,
we can plug in a bond offering, for example, and we naturally get something where we can take K3.
Okay. Now let me say, let me give you a description of what, so when R
is C with the usual absolute value, usual Archimedean absolute value. So here is a description.
Can I ask a question? Just a sec. The resulting rigid category. Yes.
You don't really mean that every step is canonical. It still depends on P, right?
P? Like this. No, no, no, no, no. P is in the norm.
Oh, okay.
Like there's different norms you can put on R. There's the usual one and then there's the
Pth power for any P between zero and one. It matches up. Yeah, it's cool. Yeah. Okay.
Right. So here is a description of the resulting rigid category.
Right. So I'm not going to, so this thing lives inside there, but because that's not familiar,
I'm going to instead embed it in something more familiar to describe this category and something
based on Hilbert spaces, which I think we can all agree on kind of nice, nice enough things.
So, and I'm going to call this the resulting rigid category. I'll call it
analytic drive category of the complex numbers. So
so this, so you can put it inside. I'll write it as an in category
of a bounded derived category of Hilbert spaces. Let's say separable Hilbert spaces.
And here all short exact sequence of split. This is like an exact
or split exact split exact category, if you like.
So you just, it's basically just a, you take finite chain complexes of Hilbert spaces,
and then you pass to the chain homotopy category, some infinity category version of that.
And then you make it big. So you pretend like it's derived category
and so on. So then it's, it's just a full subcategory of that.
And which full subcategory is it? It's the one that's generated under co-limits.
All right. And now I have to specify for you a nice class of more or less topological vector spaces.
So, well, I lost my others.
Okay. Generated under co-limits by what are called the strongly nuclear dual Frechet spaces.
What are these? These are co-limits of Hilbert spaces, sequential co-limits,
let's say injective maps. It doesn't really matter where the transition maps. So each
each and each and plus one is a compact operator
whose singular values decay rapidly.
Okay. That's the canonical class of topological vector spaces. So
they're faster than any inverse polynomial or slower or faster.
Yeah. So here's a non-example.
So there are, there are co-limits of Hilbert spaces. So there are things that feel like
in that regard, they feel like say distributions on a, on a manifold, but a non-example is the
usual space of distributions on any compact manifold, for example, S1, which is the space of
slowly increasing sequences.
Again, slower than any polynomial, it's cool to rapid decay. So there's a funny thing. I mean,
this is a, this is a basic example of what's called a, not of a nuclear dual Frechet space.
The absolute most basic one, but it's not strongly nuclear dual because the transition maps here
are like their trace class, but they're not rapid decay. They decay kind of linearly instead of
rapidly. So, but an example is if you take a holomorphic functions on a
K where K is a compact subset of C to the D.
So, you know, complex analysis or power series based stuff is allowed, but C infinity stuff is
not allowed, is the moral of the story. And this is more generally, I'll just say that we're more
generally, you know, if you have solutions of an elliptic differential, we have some elliptic
complex, elliptic differential operator on you, including C infinity, you know,
some elliptic complex, elliptic differential operator on including space and you choose a
compact subset, you're going to have this condition on the rapid decay and the transition maps.
This category, let yourself expose kind of generators that you just mentioned.
Yeah, it's not quite clear. Yeah, yeah. Does this category have any T structure on it?
It does have a T structure. Yeah, so there's an Abelian category as well,
but it has some non-Hausdorff things in it as it sort of has to. So these aren't the,
this isn't an Abelian category. Formal quotients of things like this would be the Abelian category.
Things like this are in the heart. Yeah, yeah. The T structure is kind of very naive, you could say.
Okay, go over to my notes. This is the point where when I was preparing my talk, my son,
I must have gone to the bathroom or something, my son came and drew a math monster.
So I hope you all can see it out there. It's pretty nice. He's got numbers on his face.
Making a mean expression. Okay, he's enchanted by Halloween. So, okay, so now I've told you what
the category is, right? I want to talk about K-theory, but I didn't even tell you, I didn't
tell you how the K-theory of FEMOG works. So now let me do it in this example. So
the resulting K-theory, which I'm calling
K-theory. Well, here's the trick. I said these dualizable guys are always close to compactly
generated guys. And the more precise version of that is that you can always put them inside
a compactly generated guy such that the quotient is also compactly generated. Well, that's actually
kind of automatic. So there's always the left-hand term in a localization sequence where the other
two terms are compactly generated. So if C is dualizable, where there exists a localization
sequence, C goes to D. And then K of C is just the homotopy fiber of the usual K-theory of the
compact objects here mapping to the usual K-theory of the compact objects there.
That's kind of how you can get your hands on it. Well, provided you accept that algebraic K-theory
of small categories is concrete and just debatable. But do we know what the D and the E kind of are?
Well, there's many choices. And it's an art, selecting the right one. But now in this case,
we know what they are. So now I can tell you kind of concretely. Yeah. So in our case,
so we have our D. It's just this bounded derived category here. But that's also the same thing as
the bounded. I mean, there's a single generator here, which is pick your favorite Hilbert space
of infinite dimension. And then this category is just the same thing as the bounded right category
of non-commutative ring this time with bounded operators on that Hilbert space. And when you
calculate the quotient, it's also going to be generated by a single object, just the image of
your favorite Hilbert space. But then the endomorphisms change. And what you get is,
maybe I should say perf, actually, just to be safe.
Mounded operators on Hilbert space. Modulo, the specific so-called Schatten ideal,
which actually we've already encountered. This is the ideal of compact operators
with rapid decay singular objects. Okay. But no, but this guy, this cat, this guy,
or this category is one of those types of categories I was talking about that has an
Eilenberg swindle. So it's K theory is zero. So at the end of the day, what you find is that
this analytic K theory of the complex numbers is just a shift of the usual K theory of a
rather strange ring, some analog of a Calkin algebra. So this bounded operators on the Hilbert
space modulo, this Schatten ideal. But let me make a remark that the ring structure
on KNC, which is induced by the tensor product you naturally have on this category is obscured
from this perspective. So this perspective isn't actually nice for, it's concrete, so to speak,
but it's not necessarily the best way to understand what this thing is. Just giving it to you for
comfort. You can rewrite this thing up to a shift as the K-3 of an ordinary ring. Okay.
But now I've said enough maybe to say what the conjecture is.
So I'll give on the level of homotopy groups. So pi n of this analytic K theory of the complex
numbers should be z in degree zero, and it should be c cross in degree one. But probably the best
way to understand this c cross is as uniformized, 2 pi i, c mod 2 pi i z, I guess. And then more
generally, when n is like 2m minus one, you should write this as 2 pi i to the m z.
But then if n is 2m, and this is for m positive, if n is 2m and positive, you should get zero,
generalizing our discussion about K2 of the complex numbers. So this is exactly the regulators,
right? And then you should get z if n is 2m and m is less than or equal to zero.
So there should be stuff in negative degrees as well. It's an aspect I didn't mention that
once you go to this idempotent complete context, then K3 naturally has stuff in negative degrees as
well. OK. So yeah. So let me note. So this. I'm sorry? Did I not mention that? Wait. Oh,
thank you. Thank you. Yes, I mean 2 pi i to the m. Thank you.
So note. So this suggests that. So in terms of like thinking of K3 in terms of x in some
other category, this suggests that a theory is like.
I won't bother trying to make it precise, but that's in the category of pairs.
So L filtration on the complexification. So this is a abelian group. This is a decreasing filtration
on complexification. So it's kind of mixed hodge structures without the weight filtration, you could say.
OK. And now I want to say something about the evidence for this conjecture.
Does the construction of these K groups only as abstract groups or do you see the topology on them?
In principle, you only see them as abstract groups, but let me address that more later.
Negative. So I understand X, X can have something to do with K and positive. What about negative?
It's also X. I mean, there are homes in this category.
I mean, there are homes from Z to Z minus M. Right.
So the evidence, the first bit of evidence is that it's proven true.
That's, I guess, the theorem of us in degrees less than or equal to zero.
So the part where you're just getting Z's and zero.
And also, it's probably within reach in degree one to see that you get the C cross like you expect.
It's not obvious by any means, but it's probably within reach.
Another thing is that there does exist a comparison map, natural comparison map from
so K and analytics to the expected target, expected value.
So extending the right regulator maps, basically.
So the usual, the usual K theory, algebraic K theory of C kind of maps to this naturally.
This would be if you did the naive thing of taking your category,
taking compact objects and then taking K theory instead of taking this better thing.
In fact, so in fact, there exists a commutative square of rings in the spectrum.
So K and C goes to do this one first. KU, that's the topological K theory.
That would be if you just had the Z's or just if it was just zero, Z, zero, zero, Z everywhere.
And then you have to add in some Durham data.
So you use, you can use, for example, negative cyclic homology, say over the reals, it doesn't
matter the complex numbers or periodic cyclic homology, the reals are the complex numbers.
So this is like, this is like topological or Betty, this is like Durham.
This is Durham plus filtration, so to speak.
And then the conjecture, the real conjecture is that this is a pullback
or the honest version of the conjecture, a spectrum level version.
Right, and another thing, I'm not going to get to the non-archimedean evidence, although it's
interesting. Maybe I'll just say it in words while I'm erasing. There is a non-archimedean
analog of this, say for Cp, you can identify everything. You can prove it using a theorem
of Sasha's, of humor. Then using this theorem, you can do a calculation and actually confirm
the analog of this conjecture for Cp or a variant maybe, solid variant as opposed to liquid.
It's, you know, it's fun. You see, you need to see period rings popping up.
Substrict R.
Where are we?
That bottom board. C minus sub R.
Oh, the real numbers?
Well, you don't want to do it over the rational numbers.
But over C.
Yeah, over C it's the same as over R. Yeah, I mean, as I told you.
Okay. To me, it feels more principled. Because in principle, this is a more refined thing,
but of course, it's the same thing. But anyway.
Oh, yes, and here. By the way, does this address your question earlier in the talk? Okay.
Also, this Kn functor, it actually extends in two different directions. It extends to
arbitrary complex analytic spaces.
And then, then the conjecture is that Kmc is compact based basically well related to
in the same way that K theory is related to motivic cohomology, compactly supported Deligne cohomology.
But it also extends to arbitrary, let me just say smooth, although it's not really necessary,
complex algebraic varieties.
Oh, thank you. Sorry. Yes, yes, yes, yes.
And then the conjecture is, is that K theory analytic is some version of Deligne-Beilinson cohomology.
Note that if you take an algebraic variety, you're getting a different value for it than
its analytical, which is natural. And then you're getting a different value for it than
its analytical, which is natural. But you're taking the base seed to be always analytic
in the sense that you're remembering the topology. But when you do things over it,
you can choose whether they be algebraic or analytic. You get different answers.
And this, I'm supposed to be giving evidence, but this is just a good cover.
But the point is that the functoriality
and the projective bundle formula
all match up. So the functoriality you see in compactly supported Deligne cohomology,
whichever directions you have it, you get it over that you can prove it exists here,
and same with Deligne-Beilinson and then over here. So they feel the same in that respect.
You don't get compactly supported in the second case. So there's a good reason why,
but I won't get into it. Okay. And also this kind of geometry goes into
the proof that it holds in degrees less than or equal to two. Sorry, less than or equal to zero.
So we use this extension to complex analytic spaces to get a handle on what's going on over
a point. So in that sense, it's kind of a fluid sort of formalism. And this, now I can address
your other question about whether there's extra structure on these. Yes, there is. They're all
sheaves on complex analytic spaces, which is stronger than having a topological structure.
So it's A1. Yeah, it actually would be something like A1. Yeah, A1 analytics. Yeah.
And the last thing I was going to talk about was non-acromedian analogs,
but I think I won't. So thank you for your attention.
Any questions?
It's a very vague question. Why do we not have like negative homology for like discrete fields,
but we do have negative. No, even for CP, there's nothing in negative degrees.
And it's just something. There's something about those complex numbers.
It's really not obvious. It's not obvious why it has something. I mean,
there's something to do with the Betty realization that you have this.
Nowhere else do you get it. I don't have a good answer, as you can tell.
Yeah. Oh, you just, you would just take fixed points for, you know, come to the Galois group
acting. So it's related to the pose of the gamma. Sorry. It's related to the pose of the gamma
function. Well, yeah. Yeah. No, I mean, this is, I mean, yeah. And so, I mean, this kind of thing is
what should be related to regulators and that's positive integers. So I'm speaking
and over this year, I mean, you want, I think you want these guys in the negative degrees as well.
You think about the whole L function. Yeah. Say a few words about how these definitions would
compare with more classical definitions in the K theory of operator alphabets.
Yes. Thank you for that. I'm happy for the opportunity. They proved some very interesting
theorems. For example, if you take, yeah, thanks a lot. If you take, I was looking at K theory of
bounded operators on the Hilbert space, modulo this Schatten ideal. If you look instead at
K theory of bounded operators on a Hilbert space, modulo, the ideal of all compact operators,
then this, and you take loop space, and this is KU.
With algebraic K theory? Yep, algebraic K theory. Yep. No, it's amazing. Yeah. But so,
so what's, what's the difference? Well, the difference is if you have a compact operator,
you can't define a trace. If you have a trace class operator or even better,
a rapid decay operator, you can define the trace. And that's why this is picking up more over here.
Um, there has been investigations of the analog where you replace this by the Schatten ideal P
for P positive. I've been some, I think it's a theorem of Courtney S and I hope Tom, perhaps
I forget, please don't quote me on it, but that maybe the fiber of the cyclotomic trace here is
also KU. And it would be very interesting to, but their methods, unfortunately do not reach this,
which is the truly canonical thing. But it would be very interesting if there was some way to
leverage their results, the challenge in the P greater than zero regime to get something here.
So the reason this isn't good is because it doesn't, it doesn't correspond to a dualizable
category really. And it doesn't, yeah, we're a rigid category. This is, I mean, yeah,
unfortunately they haven't investigated the only, like the truly canonical thing, but they've done
a bunch of interesting related work, which could serve as, um, stepping boards for understanding
this thing. Yes. So you kind of said that this description is bad because of the ring structure,
but then the kind of list you gave, you didn't at least talk about the ring structure. I didn't
talk about the ring structure there. Or wait. But, but so then, which means that you could still
address since you didn't talk about the ring structure, you could still address that table
from this thing conceivably. I don't understand. It didn't sound like a question.
Like you said that you prove these negative results using a totally different method,
but you have, I didn't even understand that. Sorry. Well, you have a description of the
K of the MLBK theory there. No, it's conjectural. Yeah. Wait, no, this, this, yes, yes, yes.
A description. Yeah. And you gave some answers. I mean, no, but some of them you said you proved.
Oh yeah. But can you see them? Can you understand them at all in an operator theoretic way yourselves?
Probably. Can you see where those classes are coming from in, in this update? It's not,
it's not fun. So, so the guy, it was Karubi, I should say, who found the degree minus two class
here. And you can use his method to find the same, show the same class list here.
It's fun. It's a, yeah, it's kind of the inverse to the bottom.
And the bottom in itself doesn't exist because we haven't passed the homotopy yet. But,
but, but, but it's, it's, it's a bit of a slog, but we have a clean geometric way of producing
the same class. Once you have that. So you said it's a sheath in a meditator. So if I take
like Stein manifold and like consider it's an etiquette in a conjecture, they should get like
quotient of homotopy function. Exactly. I mean, it's just, yeah, there's no, I mean, there's no
sheath cohomology in the whole, the wrong part of the linear cohomology. So you can even write
down what it is. You mentioned there is a cyclotonic tracenet. Yeah, sure. Yeah.
Can you describe the target? Oh, that's it. Thank you. Another, yeah. Here's a companion conjecture.
Let's just talk about, I mean, it's, it's actually over Q, right? It's a Q linear category. So
so forget cyclotomic, it doesn't do anything, but the companion conjecture
it's about the Hochschild cohomology over sphere spectrum Z. It doesn't matter of this. Well,
let me say for this ring. It's just, maybe I want to say suspension.
So it should just, for the Hochschild cohomology of the category I'm interested in should just be C
and degree zero. And that should correspond to the fact that you can take traces. So, but actually
this again unwinds to something that looks completely unbelievable that you can, this is
a non-unital ring and you can make the Hochschild complex there and that computes the thing, the
loops of this. And it's, but it's really the algebraic Hochschild complex with this
ring. So you're tensoring this ring together over Q and making the usual Hochschild complex.
And the claim is it's acyclic and positive degrees. And the non-archimedean analog of this is
equally unbelievable, but it was proven by my student Adriano Cordova. So take compact, now
compact and trace class is all the same in the periodic setting, but you take the Hochschild
Hochschild complex and this thing with algebraic tensor products and you can get Qt in degree zero
and you get zero in positive degrees. This proof does not go by analyzing this Hochschild complex.
It uses a whole bunch of crazy stuff, including a few months results and then just go with the
Cartesian, all sorts of nonsense. But yeah, anyway, that's yeah, but you could in principle
just try staring at this Hochschild complex and you'll, if you manage to prove it's acyclic and
positive degrees, then you'll be halfway to proving our projection. So give it a shot.
Yeah.
The multiplicative structure is the only phase level one.
Yes. Yeah. And I mean, one of the reasons I like this is because it kind of makes it plain.
But yeah, there's also, yeah, there's also a tensor structure on this category and,
you know, you know, the tape twists are multiplicative in the appropriate sense of that
kind of thing. So if you do lift that class, the minus two class up, can you then see that it's
classed in on like a bit as high a power as that non-zero by regulating it in some way and then
like you release get a kind of embedding of the answer into the thing.
I don't, because I'm sorry. Once again, I'm having trouble understanding your question.
Well, you lifted the negative two. Yes. Yes. Then you could take its powers and
you're allegedly generating all the negative stuff. Exactly.
Can you see those all non-zero by regularizing it, heating them with.
Oh, you detect them. I mean, yeah, you, you, but that's not really how the proof goes. I mean,
I know. Yeah, yeah, you can, you can detect them in topological cake here. Yeah. But it's
not right. It's not about regulators at that point, because there's no, there's no,
this is where the regulators really are. It's the, it's the ambiguity in the regulator.
That's kind of the integral thing.
It's not so, it's some form, some form of it. Yeah.
Um, that's a good question. So the top, I would say that the only, I mean,
it'd have to be in some, uh, some dagger context, some, some, some kind of, or some whatever,
you know, you know what I mean by this. And then it would probably again, just be compact.
Yeah. No, I guess the answer is I don't know. Yeah. But it should be positive that I'm sure
if I think I can answer it, but I'm not right now. Yeah.
Is this diagonal supposed to be valid for any X?
Yeah. If you put like KU of X here and yeah, yeah.
Correct. For the, for algebraic. Oh, no, no, sorry. But for only for compact analytic
varieties. Yeah.
Correct. Otherwise you'd have to put the compactly supported variants of all the things.
But okay. I mean, it's also depends on what exact, what exactly you want to mean by this.
There's a non-compactly supported variant too, but it's not directly the K theory of something.
Um, so I mean, I mean, the, the, by sort of point for anyone,
you can always get one from the other. Um, we're not even concrete or just the sheet theory.
So here you said the functionality matched up. Yeah. Like, like the, do you have like, uh,
push forward for, for all the conversions for, for like a quasi-coherent sheaves?
Look, um, I don't remember the details of anything, but yeah,
I checked all the phone for it. I mean, whatever happens, if you have one here,
you have one there. I mean, yeah. So I mean, it's going to be a little more helpful than that.
I mean, the, we have also the six functor formalism for these, uh, for this theory of
quasi-coherent sheaves we've built on analytic spaces. And so when, when you're supposed to get
them, when you're supposed to get a map on K theory is supposed to get when we have a functor
which commutes with co-limits and who's right. A joint commutes with co-limits.
So an example of that would be if you have a smooth map and you take lower shriek, right. Um,
but another example of that would be if, uh, you have an arbitrary map, uh, or sorry, you know,
uh, what was I saying? Do you have a, yeah, no, smooth map. Can you take lower shriek? Yeah.
Another example would be if you have a proper map and you take upper star. So this, yeah.
Okay. We have no further questions. Thank you, Mr. Speaker.